He dribbled past him!
过人啊
Jeez, what a lousy shot.
妈呀，这臭球
I'd do better out there myself.
还不如我上去踢呢
How many chicken racks have you had?
干几个鸡架了？
Are you watching the game or keeping watch?
这看球还是盯人呢？
However many I eat, it's not on your dime.
我干几个也不用你花钱
I've been watching all morning. My eyes are going blind.
这盯一上午了，眼睛都快盯瞎了
I don't even want to scold you two.
不爱说你俩
You can't take Xing San's word seriously.
那邢三儿的话能当真呀？
Boss!
老板
Another plate of chicken hearts.
再来盘鸡心
Coming right up.
好咧
Go easy on those. They're high in cholesterol.
那玩意儿少吃呀，胆固醇高
I ordered them for you. You are what you eat.
给你点的，吃啥补啥
Then save them for you and my brother-in-law.
那留给你跟我姐夫吧
Perfect late-night snack for you two.
正好你俩当夜宵
What are you doing?
干啥呢？
Hold onto this sketch. I've got an errand to run.
拿着这画像，我办点事去
How big an ass needs that much paper?
多大屁股用那么多张纸呀？
Am I keeping you from wiping your mouth?
我耽误你擦嘴了？
Didn't you say no bathroom breaks?
你不是不让上厕所吗？
So strict with others, so lenient with yourself.
对别人要求特多，不知道严于律己呀
How old am I? How old are you?
我多大岁数？ 你多大岁数？
Can you show some respect for the elderly?
尊重点老年人行不行？
I'm on insulin shots and still toughing it out here.
我扎胰岛素，还在这挺着呢
-No bathroom here, right?
-Not here.
-没厕所是吧？
-这没有
-That way.
-Get going. Don't crap your pants.
-往那边走
-你赶紧去吧，别拉裤兜子了
Make yourself useful. Keep your eyes peeled.
起点作用，盯住了啊
A lazy donkey always needs to piss at work.
懒驴上磨屎尿多
Pass it! Don't you know how to pass?
传，传球不会呀？
Hey, don't clear this table.
那什么，这桌别收拾啊
-I'll be right back.
-Sure thing.
-我马上回来
-好，行
(Sports Lottery Super Lotto)
（体彩大乐透）
Ah, forget it.
不管了
Play these numbers.
照这个打
You still want change?
还找钱吗？
Why not just grab some scratch cards?
整几张刮刮乐得了吧？
What's the fun in those?
整那有啥意思？
There's no skill involved.
也没啥技术含量
Those are quick.
那玩意快啊
One flip and you know.
一翻两瞪眼
Give me one, then.
妳给我来一张吧
Here. The money.
给，钱
Knock yourself out.
玩吧
-Did anyone win today?
-Yeah.
-今天有人中奖吗？
-有呀
-How many?
-Two.
-中几个呀？
-两个
Why didn't you say so earlier?
那妳不早说
It's struck twice already, no third time.
My luck's run out.
那再一再二不再三嘛 哪还轮得到我了？
It's all down to luck anyway.
那玩意得看运气吧
-You're hustling me here. Honestly...
-Well...
-妳这不坑我吗？ 妳說妳
-这…
-Boss, ten yuan's worth for me.
-Sure.
-老板，给我来十块钱的
-好咧
-Uh... all quick picks.
-Quick picks?
-那个…全要机选的呀
-机选啊
What's the fun in quick picks?
机选有啥意思？
Isn't that just wasting money?
那不浪费钱吗？
The machine's theirs.
Why would it side with you
机器是人家的，能跟你一伙啊？
and let you win?
让你中奖
Come on, you pick your own numbers.
How many times have you won?
不是，你手写的，你中过几回奖呀？
And how many times have you won with quick picks?
你机选你中几回呀？
Man, how many times have I won?
妈呀，我中了几回？
Let me tell you.
我告诉你
My car, my apartment...
我车、房
All bought with quick-pick winnings. Believe it?
我全靠机选中奖买的，知道不？
Keep bragging.
吹吧你
Hey, bragging's tax-free anyway.
反正也不上税
Buddy,
大哥
let me give you a piece of advice.
我奉劝你一句
Before you buy a lottery ticket,
买彩票之前
fill your heart with peace and devotion.
内心多一些平和和虔诚
What kind of attitude is that?
什么态度呢？
You don't know a kindness when you see one.
不识好歹
He really won't budge, soft or hard.
还真是软硬不吃
Print me a quick pick too.
给我也打张机选
To the traffic police.
去交警队
Then get another cab.
那你换个车吧
I'm not taking fares today.
今儿我不拉活
You don't have a choice.
你不拉不行
Move it.
赶紧的
Hey, what do you think you're doing?
不是，你想干点啥呀？
You know damn well what I'm doing.
我干啥你心里没数呀？
-I've got things to do.
-You don't want your cab anymore?
-我还有事呢
-车都不要了是吧？
-Trying to run?
-Bro, what are you doing? Hey...
-想跑是吧？
-哥，你干啥？ 不是
Not short on cash, huh?
不差钱呀？
Bro, easy! Wait...
哥，你轻点，不是
Your apartment and car were bought
with quick picks, right?
房子跟车都是机选买的，是不？
-Bro...
-Don't you struggle with me.
-哥
-别跟我拉扯
Don't tussle. I've had training, you know.
别拉扯，我可练过呀
The two of us, over a quick pick?
咱俩因为一个机选的事
Is this really necessary?
咱俩至于这样吗？
-Cut the crap.
-I'm telling you, my arm was hurt in a fight.
-你别跟我瞎扯
-我告诉你，我胳膊以前跟人打过仗
-Don't move...
-It's injured! Easy!
-别动…
-有伤呀，你轻点
You... what are you... hey, is this necessary?
你…你干…不是，咱至于吗？
Calling in backup, over this little thing?
还找帮手，这点事呀
You flatter yourself.
Why would I need backup to handle you?
我给你脸了，我整你我还找帮手
Ever heard of mixed martial arts?
知道综合格斗不？
Are we even in the same weight class?
是一级别的吗咱俩？
I could crush you just by sitting on you.
我压我都压死你了我
Done squirming yet?
拉完没呀？
-Go ahead.
-Found him. Get over here.
-你说
-找着了，赶紧过来
Bro, you can stop digging.
大哥，你就别掏了吧
There's nothing in my pockets.
我兜里啥也没有
I haven't had a single fare today.
今天我还没拉着活呢
He thinks we're highway robbers.
把我们当劫道的了
So... so you're not robbing me?
那…那你们不是劫财的？
Let me give you a piece of advice.
我奉劝你一句呀
In a bit, answer whatever we ask. Got it?
一会问你啥你答啥，知道不？
Just keep that peace and devotion
in your heart, and you'll be fine.
你内心就带着平和和那个虔诚就行了
Fellas, did you maybe grab the wrong guy?
几个大哥，咱是不是找错人了？
I've got no beef with you. What is this?
咱无怨无仇的，这是干啥呀？
No mistake.
没找错
You're exactly who we want.
找的就是你
Do I even know you?
我认识你吗？
The cornfield.
玉米地
You ran pretty fast.
跑得挺快呀
Got scared after you hit someone?
撞完人害怕了？
Hey, what do you mean?
不是，你啥意思？
When did I ever hit anyone?
我什么时候撞人了我呀？
Let me jog your memory.
我给你提个醒吧
The morning of October 20th,
you were driving this cab,
10月20号上午，你就开着这车
with fake plates: Hua AW357F.
套的桦AW357F的牌
Ring a bell?
想起来没？
Bro, come on, I'm just an unlicensed cabbie.
不是，大哥，我就是个开黑车的
I'm no gangster.
我不是混黑社会的
Who would I dare hit? Me, run someone over?
我敢撞谁呀？ 我撞人呢
Young man, the three of us aren't cops.
小伙子，我们仨不是警察
Hey, even if you said you were cops,
不是，你们说你们是警察
I'd have to believe it first.
我也得能信呢
-Why so chatty?
-What are you doing?
-你话怎么那么多呢？
-你干啥？
-No rough stuff. Ask nicely.
-Just answer what we ask, all right?
-你别动手，好好问
-问你啥你答啥得了嘛
What's going on?
怎么回事呀？
Here's the thing.
就是一句话
We're not after you.
我们找的不是你
We're after the person you hit.
找的是你撞的那个人
I'll say it one more time.
我再说一遍
I didn't hit anyone.
我谁也没撞
Kid, why are you so stubborn?
不是，你这个小子 你怎么这么倔呢？
If we had no evidence,
why would the three of us come for you?
要没证据，我们仨干嘛找你？
You hit someone. That's settled fact.
你撞人了，这个事落实妥妥的了
Just tell us who you hit,
只要你说出来你撞的是谁
and we'll let you go right away.
我们马上就放你走
Playing peaceful now, huh?
玩平和呢在这
Easy with him.
你轻点你呀
-Biaozi, do it.
-All right then.
-彪子，动手吧
-那行
Don't pull the knife.
你别掏刀
What knife? We can't go committing crimes.
掏什么刀？ 不能再犯罪了
-I'll cripple him.
-Bro, look at yourselves...
-我把他废了
-大哥，你看你们几个
at your age.
都这么大岁数了
Why would we go that far?
咱扯那干啥呀咱是？
Won't talk, huh?
不说是吧？
What do we do?
怎么办？
Turn him in.
报官吧
You're done for. This time you're really done for.
你废了，这回你废了
(PAUSED)
（暂停）
All right, thank you for supporting our work.
行，感谢你们支持我的工作
Oh, comrade, no need for thanks.
不是，同志，感谢就不用了
Police and people are one family, after all.
警民一家亲嘛
Then let's not stand on ceremony.
那一家人不说两家话
When can I drive my cab out of here?
我那车啥时候能开走呀？
-Go to the accident division for the paperwork.
-Sure.
-行，你去事故科办手续吧
-好咧
Comrade, he didn't just fake the plates.
There's definitely more to it.
同志，他不光套牌，肯定有别的事
Please find out who he hit.
你帮我问问他撞的人是谁
Don't you worry.
这个你放心
Hit-and-run means criminal charges, guaranteed.
肇事逃逸肯定追究刑事责任
Everything will be investigated thoroughly.
啥事都得问明白呀
-We'll notify you once we have results.
-Good.
-一有结果通知你
-好
-Head on back now.
-All right.
-赶紧回去吧
-好
-Let me know when you have results.
-Sure.
-有结果告诉我呀
-好
The name's Wang Xiang.
我叫王响
-"Xiang," as in "resounding."
-Sure...
-“响亮”的“响”
-行…
Wang Xiang.
王响
What are you really after?
你到底要查啥？
Another plate of lamb.
再来一盘羊肉
What seafood do you have?
妳家有啥海鲜呢？
-We have squid.
-Add a squid.
-有鱿鱼
-再来个鱿鱼
Don't order so much. We can't finish it all.
别点那么多，吃不了
It's not much. Add a bellflower root salad.
不多，再拌个桔梗
Go ahead. We'll order more if needed.
去吧，一会不够再点
Sure thing.
好咧
Since you two won't get things started,
I'll propose the first toast.
你俩也不张罗，那我先提一个吧
How can we start without drinks?
没酒怎么张罗呀？
How could there be no drinks?
哪能没酒呢？
Here, brother-in-law.
来，姐夫
This meal is mainly to treat Captain Ma.
这顿饭主要是请马队
That's right.
对
If it weren't for you,
要没有你呢
I wouldn't have gotten my cab back so fast.
我车也不能那么快开回来
No need to thank me.
不用谢我
Once the matter was cleared up,
naturally the cab was returned.
这事整明白了，自然车就还你了
No, you can't put it that way.
不，那话不能这么说
Without you,
要没你
it wouldn't have gone so smoothly.
这事也不能办那么痛快呀
-Right.
-Am I right?
-是
-是不？
-Come on then.
-Cheers.
-那来吧
-来
Here, eat up.
来，吃菜
Aren't you going to propose one?
你不提一个呀？
Nothing you want to say?
不想说点啥呀？
Go on, say something.
提一个吧
To Captain Ma.
谢马队
I don't want to hear that.
不听这个
Say something else.
说点别的
Like what?
啥呀？
Honestly, what should I say?
说实话吧，说啥呀？
Brother-in-law, Captain Ma is one of us.
姐夫，马队也不是外人
Just say whatever's on your mind.
有啥话直说吧
What I'd say isn't exactly solid.
我说那玩意也没啥准
Better not say it.
还是不说了
If you won't drink, let's eat.
你要不喝，咱吃
Then can I say it?
那我能说吧？
Well, who did that fake-plate car hit?
不是，那套牌车撞的人是谁呀？
You two went through all this trouble.
你俩费这么大劲
What do you want with him?
找他干啥呀？
Stop keeping it under wraps.
别掖着藏着了
It's pointless.
没意思
Since the conversation's come this far,
那嗑都唠到这了
let me tell you something interesting.
那我就说点有意思的
The person that fake-plate car hit...
套牌车撞的那个人
is the one who got Yang'er killed.
就是害阳儿的那个人
That's a bit interesting, no?
这话有点意思吧？
Interesting.
有意思
Go on then.
那你接着说吧
We got him on camera.
拍着了
There's no face here.
这脸都没有
How can you tell it's him?
你是怎么看出来的？
Look.
你看
You didn't believe me back then.
当初我说你就不相信
And you still don't believe me now.
现在你还是不相信
So what's the point of me talking?
我说这有啥意思呢？
What do you expect me to believe?
你让我信啥？
Wang Xiang,
王响
this business with Yang'er
has made you obsessed.
阳儿这事把你给整魔怔了
He's lost it, and you're losing it with him?
他魔怔了，你也陪着魔怔啊？
No, Captain Ma.
不是，马队
-It's mainly my brother-in-law...
-No, if you got to the bottom of this,
-主要我姐夫…
-不是，你要把这个事整明白了
would I still be obsessed?
我能不能魔怔？
Wang Yang committed suicide.
王阳是自杀
I told you that 18 years ago.
18年前我就跟你说了
It wasn't suicide.
他不是自杀
I know my own son.
我儿子我了解
His killer was Fu Weijun.
杀他的人就是傅卫军
Here we go again.
又来了
Haven't I told you?
我跟你说过没有？
When you were at the railway tracks,
你在火车道的时候
Fu Weijun had already been caught by us.
那傅卫军让我们警察都抓住了嘛
Then how did he get to the tracks?
那他怎么去的火车道？
Exactly. It wasn't him.
所以不是他呀
You don't have to believe me,
你可以不相信我
but when we arrested him,
可抓他的时候
so many pairs of eyes were watching.
那么多双眼睛就在那看着呢
Could they all be wrong?
能看错了？
Which is why you're wrong.
所以说你错了
You were wrong 18 years ago.
当初18年前你就错了
Everyone, calm down.
都消消气
Don't you say a word.
你别说话
Just tell me this:
你就告诉我
Fu Weijun is in prison now.
傅卫军现在在监狱里呢
How could he have gotten out
and been hit by a car?
他怎么就出来让车给撞的？
Then tell me, how did my son die?
你告诉我，我儿子怎么死的？
Why are you shouting at the two of us?
你跟我俩这吵吵啥呢？
Do you think we cops just talk nonsense all day?
我们警察在这天天胡说八道呢？
We rely on evidence, not imagination.
我们讲究的是证据，不是在这想像
Is this imagination? Isn't this evidence?
这是想像吗？ 这不是证据吗？
-How is this not evidence?
-This what?
-这还不是证据吗？
-这啥？
No face in it. If this isn't imagination,
then what is it?
脸都没有，这不是想像，这是啥？
What is this?
这是啥？
-Just tell me...
-Nothing, it's fine...
-你就告诉我
-没事呀…
It's nothing. Sorry about that.
没事，不好意思呀
It's fine...
没事…
Sorry, folks...
不好意思呀…
A little too much to drink.
借点酒劲
Both of you, calm down.
都消消气
How old are you two combined?
加一起多大岁数了？
What are you doing?
干啥呀？
Take it home, whatever it is.
有事回去说吧
Wang Xiang, you need to understand
王响，你得明白
what I'm saying.
我说的啥意思
You dwell on this day after day.
你天天想这事，天天想这事
Anyone would lose their mind.
搁谁他都得魔怔了
Whose family hasn't lost someone?
谁家不死个人？
My wife died of cancer last year.
我老伴去年癌症走的
So what? Should I stop living?
怎么的？ 我还不活了？
Is that the same thing, Captain Ma?
那能一样吗，马队？
Your wife died of illness.
你老伴是病死的
She died in a hospital, in a bed.
死在医院，死在床上
That's a peaceful, natural death.
那叫寿终正寝
My son wasn't even 20,
and he died in the water.
我儿子20岁不到，死在水里
How can I not think about it every day?
我能不天天想吗我？
Calm down.
消消气
Is the rest still coming?
还上不？
Coming? Who cares?
上啥上呀？
Can we return it?
能退不？
-Sir, we can't take dishes back.
-Then pack it up...
-大哥，这菜我们退不了
-打包…
What's with that attitude of yours?
啥态度呀妳呀？
I came here demanding some accountability,
you hear me?
我到这来就是要妳一个态度 妳知道不？
My attitude has been perfectly fine.
我一直态度挺好
-Pay up.
-What kind of attitude is this?
-赔钱
-妳们什么态度？
-The pay-compensation kind. Pay up.
-But...
-赔钱的态度，赔钱
-不是…
You...
妳…
Well, isn't that Xu-jie?
这不徐姐吗？
What's that on your... did you get a stye?
怎么起…起针眼了？
Bullshit. What stye?
别放屁，长啥针眼呢？
I had two perfect double eyelids.
我本来俩大双眼皮
Look what your wife did to me.
你看看你媳妇给我整的
Now one's single and one's double.
一单一双了都
Once I finish your other eye, we're done, right?
我把那只也给妳整完就完事了吧？
Right. You fix my eye properly
对，妳把姐给那眼睛整好了
and don't charge me for it.
妳别收人钱了
Call it a freebie.
当赠送了
You think I'd still let you touch me?
还敢让妳整呀？
If you blind me, whose fault is that?
整瞎了算谁的？
It's cold out here. Come in and talk.
门口挺冷的，进来说吧
What's wrong? Back-alley clinic scared of being heard?
怎么的？ 黑诊所怕人听见呀？
Scared of what? Everything I do is legit.
我怕啥呀？ 我这都正规的
Legit, my ass. You got a license?
你这正规啥呀？ 有资格证吗？
I'm in the process of getting one.
我正办着呢
So that's a no.
那就是没有吧
I'll have it any day now. It's coming through.
马上不就有了吗？ 这两天就下来了
This is practicing medicine without a license, you know that?
你这叫非法行医，知不知道？
Xu-jie, let's be fair here.
徐姐，咱平心而论呀
A procedure like yours would run six grand at a real hospital, no?
就妳这个项目 在正规医院得不得六千块钱？
At my place, I gave you two grand with ten percent off.
妳在我这，我给妳两千块钱打九折
You get what you pay for.
什么价格，什么服务
Don't you know that much?
妳心里没点数吗？
So I was cheap, and I deserve this? Is that it?
妳那意思我贪便宜，活该了吧？
I never said that. Listen here—
我可没这么说呀，我告诉妳
-Enough...
-Hey! Get your hands off!
-别说了…
-干什么？ 还上手
Stop wasting breath on her. Let's call the cops.
别跟她废话了，咱报警吧
No... call... call what? Don't call.
别…报…报啥报？ 别报
We've got a problem, let's work it out.
咱有问题解决问题吧
I'll pay whatever's fair, fair and square.
就该怎么赔就怎么赔
You think this is about the money?
那是钱多少的事吗？
If you two are willing to pay up,
你俩要认赔
-150 grand.
-How much?!
-15个吧
-多少钱？
150 grand? You're shaking us down!
15个？ 妳讹人呢妳？
Who are you calling a scammer?
妳說谁讹人呢妳？
I'm calling YOU scammers. So what?
我就說妳们讹人怎么的？
Is 150 grand too much?
15个多呀？
If I go blind,
我要瞎了
you're doing time, got it?
妳得进去知道不？
Enough.
别说了
Come on, sis.
不是，姐
We're all old Hualin Steel folks, right?
都桦钢老人了，是不？
We can talk anything over nicely.
那好商好量吧啥事
Do me a solid here, knock it down some.
妳给我个面子，打个折
How's ten grand sound?
一万块钱行不？
Here, take the phone. Call the cops.
来，电话，报警
Who do you think you are?
你多大脸呢？
Is that mug of yours worth 140 grand?
你那脸值14万？
Go ahead, call them. Go on...
那妳报吧，报…
Call, get her locked up for ten years.
妳报完给她抓进去，让她判十年
Go ahead.
妳报吧
See if a single cent lands in your pocket then.
妳看到时候一分钱能进妳们兜不
Think it over.
妳合计合计
Everything's open to discussion, right?
啥事好说好商量嘛
I charged you 1,800 in total,
一共收妳一千八
and bam, you demand 150 grand.
妳咣要15万
I'd love to give you 200 million—if I had it.
我还想给妳两亿呢，咱得有呀
Is any of this realistic?
切合实际吗？
How about this:
妳这么的
You refund her the 1,800,
妳把姐那一千八给人退回去
and we pay another 30 grand on top. Deal?
咱再赔三万块钱行不？
What am I, a dog you're shooing off?
你打发狗呢？
You think I'm some beggar?
你打发要饭的呢？
Give me the phone. I'm calling the cops.
给我电话，必须报警
Then how much do you want?
那妳要多少钱呀？
100 grand.
十万
-I can't come up with 100 grand.
-Haggle any more and this talk's over.
-十万块钱我拿不出来
-你俩要再讲价，咱可不谈了呀
100 grand, flat.
就十万
Signed and sealed.
签字画押的
Set in stone. No backing out.
死牌落地，不带反悔的
Careful...
慢点…
Take care now.
慢走呀
Sorry about all this, Xu-jie.
不好意思呀，徐姐
Take care, Xu-jie.
慢走呀，徐姐
Who are you "Xu-jie"-ing?
跟谁俩徐姐徐姐的呢？
She looks older than me.
瞅着比我都老
No money by end of week, we meet at the police station.
这周再见不着钱，派出所见
Got it, Xu-jie.
知道了，徐姐
Watch your step. Hold on to me.
妳看着点道，扶着点
Liu-ge.
六哥
I'm looking to sell my taxi plate.
我那车标想转出去
Can you ask around for me?
你帮我问问啊
What's it going for now?
现在啥价呀？
It dropped again?
又降了？
100 grand works too.
十个也行
I need cash.
我要现钱
I'll wait to hear from you.
那我等你信
Shit, gave them too much corn.
操，玉米喂多了
What's wrong?
怎么的了？
Why are you crying?
妳哭啥呀？
I'm not blaming you.
我又没埋怨妳
Besides, isn't it all sorted now?
再说问题不都解决了吗？
Stop crying, okay?
别哭了啊
Where am I supposed to scrape up 100 grand?
我上哪去给人整十万块钱去？
Not your problem. I've got a plan.
不用妳管，我有招
It's no big deal.
多大点事呀？
You just had to stir things up.
你就折腾吧你
Buying a car behind my back...
你背着我偷着买车
If it weren't for you, I'd have my own shop by now.
我要不是因为你 我早就把店开起来了
Would any of this have happened?
还能出这种事吗？
Okay, that's enough crying.
行了，别哭了
Don't touch me.
别碰我
Money's gone, we'll earn more.
钱没了再挣吧
Once my racing pigeons hatch,
妳等我那赛鸽一孵化
I flip them, and we're sitting on well over a hundred grand.
我一倒腾，大十几万就有了
Problems money can solve aren't real problems.
那钱能解决的问题都不是问题
Is that even a problem?
那是问题吗？
How did we let our lives end up like this?
你说咱俩怎么就把日子过成这样
Don't you worry.
妳别着急
Once my pigeons are nesting,
妳等我那鸽子一抱窝
we'll be right back on our feet.
日子不又过起来了？
We're in the capital accumulation phase.
现在原始积累阶段
Next step, we leap up a class.
下一步就跨越阶层了
Financial freedom.
就财务自由了
You know what financial freedom is?
妳知道啥是财务自由？
Making money without lifting a finger. That's freedom.
妳不干活挣钱，那叫财务自由
Money making money, you know?
钱生钱，妳知道不？
I really envy you.
我真羡慕你
You get to live in a dream forever.
能一直活在梦里
What's so bad about that?
有啥不好的？
Dreams are just a reflection of reality.
那梦也是对现实一种映射
That's Freud, you know.
那佛洛伊德嘛
Biaozi.
彪子
Let's get divorced.
咱俩离了吧
Xiaobei's room is sitting empty, right?
我看小北那屋空着嘛
Xiaobei's room isn't ours to give out.
小北那屋咱说了不算
It's fine. Try it.
挺好，你试试
I can't even stretch my legs.
这也伸不开腿呀
It's two meters long.
两公尺长呢
How about I take your room? We can squeeze in.
要不我去你那屋吧？ 咱俩挤挤吧
Forget it. I'm a light sleeper.
你行了，我觉轻
Your grinding, farting, lip-smacking full-service package—
你那咬牙、放屁、吧唧嘴一条龙服务
I can't take it.
我受不了
I'm still a guest here, aren't I?
好歹我也是个客吧？
And we're family, on top of that.
跟你还是亲戚
I'm already wounded enough from Liru.
我在丽茹那都受多大伤了
Can't you treat me a little better?
你就不能对我好点吗？
If you and Liru get divorced,
你要跟丽茹离了婚
you and I are coworkers at best.
咱俩顶多是个同事
Where are you going?
你干啥？
Kitchen.
厨房
Can I smoke in the bathroom, then?
我去厕所抽行不？
Fine.
很好
Can I at least get a pillow?
能拿个枕头不？
Wash your feet before bed.
临睡之前洗个脚呀
That smell!
都啥味呀？
What are you doing here?
你怎么来了？
What, not welcome?
怎么？ 不欢迎呀？
I'll get you a towel.
我给你拿毛巾
-Biaozi.
-What?! I'm taking a shit!
-彪子
-干啥呀？ 拉屎呢
Never mind the towel.
不用拿了
I got word on Fu Weijun.
我打听到傅卫军的消息了
He died in prison last month.
上个月他已经死在监狱里了
Dead?
死了？
(Public Telephone)
（公用电话）
Page 9532657 for me.
帮我呼9532657
Leave a message: "Jun-ge and I have arrived in Songhe."
留言就说“我和军哥到松河了”
Boss.
老板
Lend me a couple tokens.
借两个币
Who borrows these things?
这玩意还有借的？
Got money, you play. No money, go home.
有钱就玩，没钱就回家去
When my folks get back, I'll pay you back, okay?
我等我爸妈回来了 把钱还你不得了吗？
-Just this once.
-No can do.
-我就借一次
-借不了
Now scram.
赶紧起开
50 yuan in tokens.
50的币
What's up?
怎么的了？
Out of tokens?
没币了？
Here, take two.
给你俩
Thanks, bro.
谢谢哥
What were you playing just now?
你刚才玩啥游戏了？
The King of Fighters.
《格斗天王》
Any good at it?
你玩得好不？
I'm okay.
还行
I don't like playing against the machine.
我不爱跟机子打
How about a couple rounds with me?
你要不陪我打两局吧？
I, uh...
我就…
Win, and it costs you nothing.
赢了不用你花钱
Lose, and you use my tokens.
输了用我币子
Deal.
行
I'll drop the coin for you.
我帮你投币
What's your name?
你叫啥名呀？
Shen Hui.
沉辉
Bro.
哥
You're back?
回来了？
Let's play a couple more rounds.
再玩两局去
I'm done. My mom's waiting at home.
我不玩了，我妈还在家等我呢
Who are you trying to fool?
你糊弄谁呢？
Don't you live at your grandma's?
你不住你姥姥家吗？
Aren't your folks away on a trip?
你爸妈不都出远门了吗？
They're back?
回来了？
What, did they fly home?
坐的飞机呀？
I... I really can't play anymore.
我…我真不玩了
My grandma's gonna start worrying.
我姥姥在家该等着急了
How can you just turn your back on me?
你怎么翻脸不认人呢？
Is that all our friendship's worth?
咱俩交情就这么浅吧
Fine.
行
Pay me back for all those tokens.
你把以前币子的钱给我
I... I don't have any money.
我…我没钱
I...
我…
I... I'm broke.
我…我没钱
No money? Then what do we do?
没钱怎么办呀？
N... nothing in here either.
这…这里也没钱
-I... I really have nothing.
-We'll tell your teacher!
-真…真没钱
-告诉你们老师呀
Bro.
哥
My brother asked you something.
我哥问你呢
It's fine if you've got no money.
你要是没钱也行
What'll you trade for it?
愿意拿啥换呢？
What'll you trade?
拿啥换呢？
Bro, what do you want?
哥，你要换啥？
Your hand.
手
A foot works too.
脚也行
Let me go... please, bro, I'm begging you...
放我走…哥…我求你了
Let me go, don't...
你放我走，你别…
Bro...
哥…
Bro, let me go, please, don't...
哥，你让我走吧，哥，别…
No... let me go, bro.
别，你让我走吧，哥
Don't...
别…
"Typically attached at both ends to two
“通常两端附着在两块
or more bones.
或两块以上的骨骼上面
One: master the anatomical arrangement of skeletal muscles
一、掌握骨骼肌的解剖结构排布规律
and their accessory structures.
及其肌的辅助装置
Two: master the trapezius
二、掌握斜方肌
and the location and function of the latissimus dorsi.
背阔肌的位置和功能
Three: master the pectoralis major
三、掌握胸大肌
and the location and function of the serratus anterior,
和前锯肌的位置和功能
the location, form, and function of the diaphragm,
膈的位置形态和功能
and the names and locations of its three openings."
以及膈的三个裂孔的名称位置”
What's wrong, auntie?
怎么的了，大娘？
What happened?
出啥事了？
It's all my fault.
都怪我
Going so far away to see a doctor...
跑这么远看病…
Otherwise little Hui wouldn't have gotten hurt this bad.
要不小辉也出不了那么大的事
Stop that wailing.
别嚎丧了
I'll go check out.
我退房去
Don't let it eat you up too much.
你也别太上火了
A broken arm is just an external injury.
胳膊断了就是外伤
It heals up fine.
好养
What did you say?
妳說啥？
But next time, it might not just be an arm.
不过再有下一次，就不一定伤哪了
Go home with auntie and heal up.
好好和大娘回去养病
And don't come back.
别再回来了
You will die by my hand, sooner or later.
妳早晚死我手里
I mean it.
我说到做到
Sooner or later,
早晚
you'll die by my hand.
死我手里
Yang'er, dinner's ready.
阳儿呀，吃饭了
I'm not eating, Ma.
我不吃了，妈
What's wrong, Ma?
妳怎么了，妈？
You okay?
没事吧？
I feel a bit sick.
有点难受
What's wrong?
怎么的了？
It's just a passing spell.
就这么一阵
Sit down and eat something, it'll pass.
坐下吃点东西就好了
It's just the cooking fumes.
就是油烟熏的
Eat something and you'll be fine.
吃点东西就好了
Come on, you... sit and keep me company, eat a little.
来，你…你也坐下陪妈吃点
Come on.
快点
All your favorites.
都是你爱吃的
Still mad at your dad?
还跟你爸生气呢？
Your dad means well too.
你爸也是为你好
He's just scared Xing San won't let it go and it'll ruin your factory placement.
他不是怕邢三儿不依不饶地 影响你进厂的事吗？
After hitting you, no one hurt more than him.
打完你，他比谁都心疼
He regrets it to death.
都后悔死了
He didn't sleep a wink last night.
昨天一晚上都没睡
Woke up with two big blisters on his lip.
早上起来嘴上起俩大泡
How could I not be mad?
我能不生气吗？
On the street, in front of all those people, he just hit me.
那大街上那么多人，伸手就打
Besides, is getting into the factory really that important?
再说进不进厂有那么重要吗？
Right.
是
Only factory work counts as a real job?
就厂里工作是正经工作
And what I do isn't a real job?
我那就不是正经工作吧？
It's all labor. How does he get to rank it high and low?
都是劳动 怎么到他这还分个高低贵贱了？
Look,
这事吧
you really should try to understand your dad.
你也真得理解你爸
Our generation,
我们这代人
we got used to having our lives arranged for us.
那是被安排惯了
As kids, with so many children at home,
你看小时候在家里孩子多
you obeyed your parents in everything.
啥都得听父母的
Grown up, out in the collective,
你长大了在集体里
of course you obeyed your leaders.
那肯定得听领导的呀
People like us, our whole lives, we felt like...
你像我们这辈子就觉得我们那个…
that around us,
这个身上
there was a circle.
那是有个圈的
We stayed right there,
我们就在那
plodding along inside that circle, step by step.
按部就班地在圈里那么走着
Nobody asked why.
也没人问为啥
Nobody ever wandered outside it.
也没人到圈外遛达过
Even stepping on the line was scary.
就连踩了个线都害怕
The world's changing so fast now.
现在这个世界变化也是快
Every generation has its own way of living.
哪代人都有哪代人活法
Someday, when you have kids,
将来你有了孩子
you might not figure them out either.
你也不一定能整明白
But understood or not,
但是明不明白
a father and son are always father and son.
那爷俩永远都是爷俩
Don't hold a grudge against your dad. Hear me?
不能跟你爸记仇，听见没？
I don't hold grudges against him.
我不跟他记仇
I'm not petty like him.
我可没他那么小心眼
That's good.
那就好
Come on, eat. Hurry up.
来，吃饭，快点
Eat something.
吃点东西
Here.
来
Ma.
妈
I need to go out for a bit.
我想出去一趟
Eat something before you go.
你吃点东西再走
I'm good.
不吃了
All right, go on then. Back early.
行了，那你去，早点回来呀
I'm off, Ma.
那我去了啊，妈
Bye, Ma.
走了啊，妈
Hey—don't go any further in.
别…别往里走了
No late show today.
今儿没夜场
I'm here for Shen Mo.
我找沈墨
We made plans.
我们俩约好了
You're here this early?
怎么来这么早？
"Titanic"?
“《铁达尼号》”？
We couldn't watch it together last time.
上次没能一起看
Here's your chance to make up for it.
这次给你个机会补上
This is Wang Yang.
这就是王阳
This is Fu Weijun.
这是傅卫军
I'll go see if I can get it playing.
那我去试试能不能放
Hey buddy, you just met Shen Mo, right?
哥们，你跟沈墨刚认识的吧？
Never heard her mention you either.
我也没听她提过你
Hey, I'm talking to you.
我跟你说话呢
He can't hear you.
他听不见
You could've said so.
你早说呀
Almost swung at him.
差点就动手了
The hell's he mean?
他啥意思他？
My brother says you're a bit slow.
我弟说你有点傻
Your surname's Shen.
妳姓沉
So why's your brother a Fu?
妳弟为啥姓傅啊？
My brother's a year younger.
我弟比我小一岁
After my parents died,
我爸妈没了以后
we went to live with my uncle.
我们俩就去了我大爷家
My aunt didn't want him—his ears were bad.
我大娘嫌他耳朵不好，不想要他
So they gave him to a family in Hualin.
就把他给了桦林的一家人
That family named him.
名字是那家起的
He got used to it.
他也叫惯了
Then that family had a kid of their own
后来那家自己要了孩子
so he went to the orphanage.
他就去了福利院
I tested into Hualin Med just to see him.
我往桦医考也是因为能见着他
He's the only family I've got left.
我就他这么一个亲人了
Isn't there one more now?
现在不是又多了一个吗？
Cui Guodong.
崔国栋
Down here.
在下边呢
Who found it?
谁发现的？
The patrol team.
联防队的
-Right in this drainage ditch.
-Let me.
-就在这斗沟里边
-我来
Easy there.
你慢点
Move, let me see.
躲开我看看
Step aside.
往边上点
Didn't you mark some underground drain points?
你不是划了几片地下管道排污点吗？
Had the patrol team sweep them for us.
安排联防队的帮咱们扫了
They just got to this spot.
刚扫到这地方
That Wang Xiang, huh.
行呀，这王响
What is it?
怎么的了？
This killer's a fucking monster.
这凶手太他妈没人性了
Found a backpack in the pipe too.
管道里还找到一个书包
Inside's a meal card from Hualin Med.
包里有一张桦医的饭卡
Leave the feelings out. Work.
别带情绪，干活
Move along...
散了…
Stop looking.
别看了
Search it real careful.
查仔细点呀
Reading this junk all day—how'll you get into college?
净看这破玩意，能考上大学？
("The Death of Ah Lu")
（《阿橹之死》）
"At a moment like this
“这样的时刻
let me die before my father
让我殇于父亲之前
let my mother, with her final elegy,
让母亲以挽歌的绝唱
keep vigil for me, and for the earth's four seasons"
为我，也为大地上的四季守眠”
What kinda crap poem is this?
啥破诗呀？
No meter, no rhyme.
不合辙，不押韵的
Where'd it go?
哪去了呢？
Good Lord.
妈呀
This room looks like it got robbed.
这屋怎么跟进贼了似的呢？
Dad.
爸
What's this thing doing here?
这玩意怎么在这呢？
I haven't used it in years.
我多少年都不用它了
Wore it hiking with Qu Bo a couple days back.
前两天我跟曲波爬山的时候穿来着
This thing beats the cold.
这衣服抗冻
Hiking what?
爬啥山呢？
A snow mountain?
雪山啊？
Where's our old map gone?
咱家老地图哪去了呢？
I remember sticking it in a cookbook.
我记着夹到一个菜谱里头了
It's up here.
在这上面呢
What's it doing up there?
你放那干啥玩意你？
No—
不是
What do you want the map for?
你找地图干啥呀？
The dismemberment case.
碎尸案的事
Helping the police canvass the plant.
帮警方在厂里搞搞排查
I'm briefing Xing San and his bunch.
我给邢三儿他们开个会
Wait, you're skipping lunch?
不是，你不吃午饭呀？
This matters more than lunch.
这个事比吃饭的事大
You never stop, do you?
一天不够你忙活的
Master Wang.
王师傅
That train sits any longer, it'll rust shut.
火车再不开，都要上锈了吧
Relax.
放心吧
With me around, not even a lug nut rusts.
有我在，螺丝帽都上不了锈
It'll outlive you.
你活不过它
Isn't that Security's kettle?
这不保卫科的壶吗？
New post, Master Wang?
转岗了，王师傅？
Been given other duties lately.
最近抓点别的工作
Giving Security some training.
给保卫科上上课
You? Training them?
你给他们上课？
Gotta lecture your workshop sometime too.
什么时候给你们车间也上上课
The title:
题目就是…
"Stay Alert, Keep Your Eyes Peeled"
“提高警惕，擦亮双眼”
No manners at all.
什么素质这？
Master Wang.
王师傅
Don't go.
别走啊
The meeting hasn't started.
这会还没开呢
Where is everyone?
人呢？
Meeting's at one. Where's Security?
一点钟开会，保卫科的人呢？
Master Wang.
王师傅
Thing is, Captain Ma just called me.
这不我刚才接到马队长电话了吗？
Says the plant sweep's gotta be us two teamed up.
说咱们厂的摸排还得是咱俩配合
The moment I heard that,
我这一听
I felt solid.
心里有底了
Cut the crap.
别整用不着的
About our internal sweep,
关于咱们内部摸排的事
here's my thinking.
我是这么考虑的
Master Wang,
王师傅
here's where things stand.
现在有这么个情况
We've picked up a bit of his trail.
我们现在已经摸着他一点边了
Who?
谁啊？
Don't know who he is yet.
还不知道他是谁
But looks like the killer did show his face in our plant.
但凶手好像还真在咱们厂里冒过头
Why's Security empty?
咱保卫科为啥没人？
All out manning the net.
都去布控去了
The net?
布控？
That's right.
对了
Well? Find anything?
怎么样？ 有啥发现没有？
Nothing.
没发现
Dazhi,
大志呀
tell Master Wang
你给王师傅讲讲
everything you saw that night.
你那天晚上都看着啥了
So, that night,
就那天晚上吧
I'd just come off shift.
我刚交完班
Carrying my stuff, figuring I'd hit the baths.
我拎着东西，我寻思去搓个澡呢
I'm walking along by the furnaces, walking...
我顺着炉子那边，我就走啊走
walking...
走啊走
when all of a sudden
突然之间
I hear a noise.
我就听着点啥动静
What noise?
什么动静？
When I stop, it stops.
就是我一停，他就没声了
When I walk, it walks too.
我一走，他也跟着走
So I look up along the furnace.
我就顺那炉子，我就往那一看
And?
啥呀？
There's a guy in a protective suit
我看见那人穿个防护服
standing on top of the furnace.
在炉子上面站着呢
He turns around—
他一回身
the face is blank.
脸是空的
Blank face?
脸是空的？
Bullshit.
瞎扯呢
If I'm lying, I'm a bastard.
我要撒一句谎，我是这个
Wait—you couldn't see his face at all.
不是，你五官啥都看不见
So how do you figure he's the killer?
你根据啥判断他是凶手呢？
-Well, it's...
-Yeah, based on what?
-那不是…
-根据啥吧
Think about it.
你想呀
A guy who cuts a person into slices—
那人能把这个人切成一片一片的
you telling me he ain't evil?
你说他恶不恶？
There's a killing aura on his head.
那脑瓜顶都带煞气呀
Dazhi saw it. Did you?
大志瞅见了，你瞅见没有？
See?
你看看
Can't see his face, but you saw an aura?
五官啥都看不见，能看着煞气？
This is pointless. You two, beat it.
扯别的没有用，你俩先撤吧
Wang Xiang, listen to me.
王响，我跟你讲
He came once.
这人能来第一回
No guarantee he won't come twice.
他就保不齐还能来第二回
I've thrown all of Security out there.
我把保卫科的人都给派出去了
Every plant gate,
各厂厂口
every main road—
各主要交通干道
if it can be covered, I've covered it.
能布的我都给它布上
Male, under 180 cm,
男的，不到180公分
killing aura on his head.
脑袋顶上带煞气
Under 180 cm, male,
不到180公分，男的
aura on the head.
脑袋有煞气
This plant's got 800 of those, easy.
我们厂没一千，有八百
People can barely eat—who ain't got an aura?
饭都快吃不上了，能没煞气吗？
Wang Xiang, you're an old-timer of this plant.
王响，你是咱厂的老同志
Show a little awareness.
你得有点觉悟呀
The smelting shop is the prime spot he was seen.
冶炼车间 可是看着那个人的第一案发现场
I'm saving it for you.
我把它留给你了
Why not report straight to Captain Ma?
不是，为啥不直接汇报给马队呢？
It's just your word, no proof.
你口说无凭吧
So? You staking this spot or not?
你就说这个点你蹲不蹲
-You won't, I hand it to someone else.
-What?
-你不蹲，我现在交给别人
-什么？
Who says I won't? Course I'll stake it!
干什么不蹲呢？ 怎么就不蹲呢？
But what would the killer want at the smelting shop?
问题是这凶手到这冶炼车间干啥呀？
Catch him and ask him yourself.
一会你抓着他了，你自己问他
-What's this?
-What? A whistle.
-啥呀？
-啥？ 哨啊
What for?
干啥呀？
Blow it the second you spot something.
吹吧，一会你发现有啥情况了
Backup swarms in from all directions.
这四面八方增援呀
Here.
拿着
You take a two-hour watch.
你蹲俩点
I'll come relieve you.
我过来换你
You?
你？
Ten to ace, pair of sevens.
十到A，俩七
Lemme see your hand.
我看你牌
-Damn.
-You're short a pair of twos.
-我去
-你这差俩二
You play like absolute garbage.
你这牌打得稀烂稀烂的
-Again... deal.
-Come on... Chief Xing.
-来…再来
-来…邢科
There's still a guy in the smelting shop.
熔链车间里还有个人呢
What? You wanna cover his shift?
怎么的？ 你想替他班呀？
Not a chance.
我可不去
He dreams of earning glory, don't he?
不作梦都想立功吗？
Let him snap out of it.
让他清醒清醒
A lousy driver reaching into my Security Section.
你一个臭开车的 你把手伸我保卫科来
City Bureau? So what?
你市局怎么的？
Detective captain? So what?
你刑警队长怎么的？
I'm fucking laying it down here:
我他妈把话撂这
inside Hualin Steel, none of it flies.
只要是在桦钢，不管用
-Third Brother's the man...
-Exactly.
-三哥厉害…
-就是
Damn right.
就是
Chief Xing.
邢科
But what if Dazhi really saw the killer?
万一大志看着的真是凶手呢？
Would a real killer get caught by him?
真凶手能让他抓着呀？
He's playing a cute little game
算盘打得挺好呀
thinks this'll be his big comeback.
还想靠这个翻身呢
Liru.
丽茹
Here.
来
What took you so long?
你怎么才来呀？
I rushed over from your hospital.
我从妳医院那赶过来的
My hospital? We said we'd meet here.
上我医院干啥？ 不约在这见面吗？
Something came up at the plant office.
厂办有点突发状况
Old Zhao—Director Zhao—got jumped by two workers in the canteen.
那老赵赵主任 让俩工人堵食堂里一顿揍
Blood spraying everywhere.
那血哗哗往外滋
I was out the door and they called me back.
我都出来了，又给我叫回去了
Those office guys can't handle shit.
就厂办那几个也不扛事呀
I don't go back, it all falls apart.
那我不回去，控制不了局面
I'm off work. Spare me the plant talk.
我都下班了，不想听厂里那些事了
Sorry—kept you waiting till you starved.
不好意思呀，让妳等饿了
You only bought one?
就买一个呀
We watching the movie or not?
电影还看不看？
We are. I picked it special.
看呢，这片我特意选的
A love story. Real romantic.
搞对象的，特浪漫
Hang on, let me park my bike.
妳等我一下，我停个车呀
Where'd you get that roast sweet potato?
妳那烤地瓜在哪买的？
Get me one too.
也帮我买一个吧
Some pick...
这片选的
Never knew romance could be like this.
没想到这么搞对象呀
From the title, I figured Yu Dafu, Lin Huiyin, that stuff.
看片名我以为讲郁达夫、林徽因啥的
It's pretty romantic, actually.
这片挺浪漫的
Just a bit shaky. Making me dizzy.
就是有点晃，迷糊
That actor kinda looks like you.
我瞅这男演员长的跟你还有点像呢
Oh yeah?
是吗？
People used to say I belonged in the movies.
以前他们老说我适合拍电影
Then I went all-in on academics. Missed the boat.
后来一心搞学术，耽误了
Did my brother-in-law tell you my basics?
姐夫跟妳說我的基本情况了吗？
Who?
谁？
Master Wang.
王师傅
He... didn't really say much.
也…也没怎么说
Well, here's the deal.
是这么个情况
Career first, then family, right?
不都说先立业再成家吗？
I'm right in the rising phase of my career.
我现在就是正好处在事业的上升期
Plant office, after Director Zhao, it's me.
那厂办除了赵主任，也就我了
Speak normally. I can hear you.
你正常说话，我能听见
Freud said it:
佛洛伊德说过吧
"A mentally healthy person can do two things:
“一个精神健康的人都能做到两件事
work with devotion
认真工作
and love"
以及爱人”
On the work front,
工作这一块
I've basically left everyone in the dust.
我基本上已经做到一骑绝尘了
All that's left is love.
现在就差爱人了
Who's Freud?
谁是佛洛伊德呀？
A scholar.
一个学者
Studies dreams, mostly.
主要研究作梦的
He get an apartment?
他分房了吗？
Nope. He's not with our plant.
那没有，他不是咱厂的
Did you get one?
你分房了吗？
Any day now.
指日可待了
Old Zhao and I have explored the matter in depth.
我和老赵为这事已经深入地探讨过了
You see,
妳不知道
Director Song values talent.
宋厂长那人爱才
With my work ability,
以我的工作能力
the next round's no problem.
赶上下一拨问题不大
Liru.
丽茹
So, on the dating front,
这个处对象这块
what's your type?
妳喜欢啥类型的？
I like the mature type.
我喜欢成熟型的
Then I've got a huge edge.
那这一点我太有优势了
What edge?
你有啥优势呀？
People say I look a bit old for my age.
他们都说我多少有点显老
Watch the movie. Stop squirming.
你看电影吧，别老动弹
Your hair.
妳头发
What's so good about it?
有啥好看的呀？
Two grown men rolling around up there.
俩大老爷们在上面动来动去的
Liru.
丽茹
Wait up—I'll see you home.
妳等我一下，我送妳呀
Hop on.
上车
Aren't you heading back to the workers' dorm?
你不回青工宿舍吗？
It's not on your way.
咱俩不顺路
Isn't the earth round?
地球不是圆的吗？
Off-route or not, a few extra steps gets me there.
再不顺路，多走两步也到了
Really, no need. Thanks.
真不用了，谢谢呀
Let's pick another movie sometime.
哪天咱再选个片看吧
We'll see. I'm off.
回头再说吧，我先走了
Who pulled my valve core?
谁把我气门芯拔了？
Sweet potato man—did you see who?
卖烤地瓜的，你看见没？
Master Wang.
王师傅
Master Wang, you hungry?
王师傅，你饿不？
Let's go find a spot to eat.
咱俩出去找个地方吃点啊
Stand up first.
你先站起来
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Turn around.
转一圈
What are you doing?
干啥呀？
How tall?
多高？
180 centimeters.
180公分
Really?
有吗？
178.5 barefoot.
净量178.5公分
180 in heels.
穿带跟的180公分
I mean, you...
你说你
You're a factory office guy.
一个厂办的
Why wear smelter overalls?
穿着个冶炼的工作服干啥玩意？
Isn't that a safety hazard?
不安全生产吗？
Don't you need work clothes in the smelter?
那不进冶炼不都得穿工作服吗？
You play it real safe.
活得挺仔细
Sit down.
坐下吧
How did you know I was here?
你怎么知道我在这呢？
I went to the locomotive depot for you.
我去机务段找你去了
They said you were at a Security Section meeting.
说你给保卫科开会去了
So I went to Security for you.
我又去保卫科找你
They told me to check the overhead crane.
说让我到航吊这找找
And I actually dug you out here.
没想到真到这把你给扒拉出来了
Is that how you talk?
会说话不？
Who says "dug out" about finding someone?
你家找人叫扒拉啊？
That's not what I meant.
不是那意思
-This is "digging out."
-Yeah.
-这叫扒拉
-是
Besides, I revealed myself on purpose.
另外，我是主动暴露目标
Otherwise, could you have found me?
要不然你能找着我呀？
Right...
是…
You were so well hidden.
你那多隐蔽呀
I... I just misspoke.
我…我用词不当了嘛
Stop eating that lousy potato.
这破土豆子别吃了
Let's go find a place to eat and talk.
咱俩出去找个地方边吃边聊吧
My treat.
我请你
No merit, no reward.
无功不受禄
Why are you treating me?
你请我吃啥饭？
It's about me and Liru.
我和丽茹那事嘛
Put in another push for me.
你再帮我再使使劲吧
You need my push?
用我使劲呀？
Didn't you take her to a movie?
不看电影去了吗？
Don't bring it up.
别提了
The movie choice was a bit of a mistake.
那片选得多少有点失误呀
Was that the movie's fault?
那是片的事吗？
No, Master Wang.
不是，王师傅
Would I let you help for nothing?
我能让你白帮忙吗？
Where'd this liquor come from?
这酒哪来的呀？
Old Song gave it to me.
老宋给的
Song Yukun gave you liquor?
宋玉坤送你的酒？
I got my classmate to tutor his son in English.
我找我同学给他儿子补外语嘛
Didn't take money.
没收钱
So he gave me this.
他给我的
Said this liquor's got age.
说这酒有年头了
By age, it'd be your elder.
论年头，你得管它叫大爷
As long as you fix things with Liru and me,
只要你把我跟丽茹的事整明白了
I'd call it Grandpa.
我叫它爷爷都行
Seriously.
真的
Is the factory office busy these days?
厂办现在忙不忙？
Why?
怎么了？
If not—I'm canvassing the factory now, right?
要不忙的话 我现在不是在厂里摸排吗？
Lend me a hand.
你帮我搭个手
Sure, no problem.
行呀，没问题呀
Point, and I'll strike.
你指哪，我打哪
Then about me and Liru...
那我跟丽茹那事
Just wait for word.
听信吧
Is it done?
熟了吗？
Break off a piece for me to taste.
掰一块我尝尝
So good.
真香呀
Captain Ma.
马队
This is Shen Mo's counselor.
这是沈墨的辅导员
-Ma Desheng, Criminal Police.
-Hello.
-刑警队马德胜
-你好
Well?
怎么样？
Is it Shen Mo's?
是沈墨的东西吗？
Well... let's sit and talk.
那什么…咱坐下说吧
Shen Mo tested in from Songhe.
沈墨是从松河考上来的
She never talked much.
平时话也不太多
A quiet girl.
挺安静一女孩
Grades above average, I'd say.
学习成绩中上水平吧
Never gave us much worry.
也没怎么让我们操过心
But a while back,
但是前一段时间
something unusual came up.
有个挺特殊的情况
What situation?
啥情况呀？
What? You can't say?
怎么？ 不能说呀？
Where'd these come from?
哪来的？
Early on the 20th,
20号一早
these photos and the report letter
这些照片和举报信
were posted on the school cafeteria bulletin board.
就贴在学校食堂的那个宣传栏上
The letter also said
信里还说
Shen Mo worked as a call girl in a sex venue.
沈墨在色情场所当小姐
Drinking and sleeping with clients.
陪酒、陪睡
Why wasn't it reported?
怎么没报警呀？
School leaders feared it would hurt the school's name.
校领导说怕这事影响学校声誉
Some students also told me before
之前有一些同学也跟我反映过
her off-campus ties were complicated too.
沈墨在校外的关系也挺复杂
A boy kept coming to school for her.
有个男孩老来学校找她
Right... that kid even wrote a self-criticism at our office.
对…那小子还来我们教务处写过检查
Master Wang, let's call it a day.
王师傅，今天到这吧
The office might look for me—I should head back.
我怕厂办找我，我得回去了
What the hell? That's filthy.
什么玩意？ 太脏了吧
Easy—this is quality fabric.
你轻点，我这料子的我这
Shine it further in.
往里边照
Further in.
往里
That's the limit.
极限了
This one...
就这个…
Don't move. This one.
别动，就这个
Master Wang.
王师傅
Over here.
在这呢
Something's happened, Master Wang.
出事了，王师傅
What is it?
怎么的了？
Your wife called.
嫂子打电话
Said your son was taken by the police.
说你儿子被公安局给带走了
(Hualin Municipal Public Security Bureau)
（桦林市公安局）
(The People's Police Serve the People)
（人民公安为人民）
What's going on?
怎么回事？
I'm asking you what's going on.
问你怎么回事
Master Wang, don't panic yet.
王师傅，先别着急呢
There's a case.
有个案子
We brought him in to ask some questions.
找他过来了解一下情况
We're done. Take him home.
都问完了，领他回去吧
What case?
什么案子？
Stay there.
站那
Did I say you could go?
让你走了吗？
Um... is Captain Ma in?
那个…马队在不在？
Go on over.
过去吧
Keep an eye on him for me.
你帮我看着点
Captain Ma.
马队
I thought you weren't in.
我以为你不在呢
Seeing you puts me at ease.
你在我就放心了
What's happened to my Yang'er, Captain Ma?
我们家阳儿怎么的了，马队？
Wang Yang is your son?
王阳是你儿子呀？
That's right.
对呀
He has a girlfriend named Shen Mo. You knew?
他有个女朋友叫沈墨 这事你知道吗？
Shen Mo?
沈墨？
I didn't know he had a girlfriend.
我不知道他有什么女朋友呀
You two go home and talk it over.
你们爷俩回去唠去吧
I'm done asking.
我问完了
Tell Wang Yang he's not to leave Hualin for now.
回去嘱咐王阳这段时间不许离开桦林
We may question him anytime.
我们随时有可能找他问话
Okay.
好
Captain Ma.
马队
-I did some canvassing...
-Master Wang.
-我进行了一下摸排…
-王师傅
Don't come to the bureau without cause.
没事少来公安局吧
And stop fretting over this case.
这案子你也别瞎操心了
Just drive your train.
好好开火车
Aren't I your Watson?
我不是华生吗？
Read fewer novels.
小说少看
I like Chandler.
我喜欢钱德勒
Guodong, see Master Wang out.
国栋，送一下王师傅
What... what-dler?
什么…什么德勒？
Master Wang.
王师傅
Get going.
赶紧走吧
Okay.
好
Captain Ma, I...
马队，我…
Okay.
好
You just had to stir up trouble.
折腾吧你就
A girlfriend pops up out of nowhere.
蹦出个女朋友来
What's with this girl?
这女的怎么回事呀？
I told the police everything I should.
该说的我都跟警察说了
She's dead, you know?
她死了，你知道不？
I told you not to work at that dump.
就不让你去那个烂糟地方上班
You boasted you just had to go.
炫耀说非得去
Just wait.
等着吧
When we're home, I'm locking you up.
回去就把你关起来
Once this is all cleared up,
把事查清楚了
then I'll let you downstairs.
再把你放下楼
Stop.
站住
Will running solve anything?
你跑能解决问题吗？
Just talk it out—isn't that enough?
有啥事说清楚不就完了吗？
Where's Yang'er?
阳儿呢？
Why isn't Yang'er back?
阳儿怎么没回来？
He'll be back soon, right behind me.
一会自己就回来了，前后脚的事
What did the police say?
警察怎么说的？
Nothing much. It's fine.
没怎么说，没事
If it's nothing, why'd they take him?
没事警察能找他吗？
You... wait up, I'm talking to you.
你…你等等我，跟你问你话呢
No—I called you
不是，我打电话给你
just to pick up our son, right?
不就让你接儿子吗？
So where is he then?
你给我接哪去了？
God, my heart's been pounding like crazy.
妈呀，我心都突突毁了
Is Yang'er really okay?
阳儿真没事呀？
Don't lie to me.
别糊弄我呀
He's my own son. Would I let him get hurt?
自己的儿子，我能让他有事吗？
Then when's he coming back?
那他啥时候回来呀？
Stop following me.
妳别跟着我
My head's buzzing. I'll lie down a bit.
脑瓜子嗡嗡的，我躺会
God, mine's buzzing too.
妈呀，我也嗡嗡的
(Forensics Lab)
（法医室）
That's enough.
行了
Captain Ma, this is Shen Mo's family.
马队，这是沈墨的家属
They came from Songhe for the identification.
从松河赶过来做辨认的
This is our sub-bureau's Criminal Police captain, Ma Desheng.
这是我们分局的刑警队长，马德胜
Hello.
你好
Captain Ma.
马队长
My hometown is Hualin too.
我老家也是咱们桦林的
I worked here in Hualin years ago.
早些年我在这个桦林工作过
I know some leaders in your police system quite well.
跟你们公安系统有些领导都比较熟
You done?
说完了吗？
Li Qun, take these two to the office first.
李群，先带二位去办公室
Let's go.
走吧
Anything else?
还有什么事吗？
Well, the case is still under investigation.
这不案子还在侦查阶段吗？
We need to ask about Shen Mo's recent situation.
得跟你了解一下沈墨的近况
Here's the thing.
是这样
I've already bought my return ticket.
我已经买了回程的车票
You know trains wait for no one.
你知道这火车可不等人呀
I have a lot waiting for me back in Songhe.
我回松河还有好多事等着我去处理呢
We can't exactly chat on the train, can we?
那也不能上火车上聊去吧？
We're all busy.
都挺忙
Fine.
好
Then we'll cooperate.
那我们配合配合
Stop crying.
别哭了
Let's go.
走吧
Captain Ma.
马队
Why does he seem so off to me?
我怎么瞅着他那么别扭呀？
Off how?
哪别扭啊？
To me, you two actually look quite alike.
我瞅着你俩长得倒挺相像的
What nonsense.
净瞎扯
I mean, he doesn't look like her real dad.
我是说瞅着不像亲爹呀
He's not her real dad.
本来就不是亲爹
He's her uncle.
她大爷
He adopted Shen Mo.
沈墨是他收养的
(The People's Police Serve the People)
（人民公安为人民）
Come here a sec.
你过来一下
Look.
你看
You've got sharp eyes.
你眼神好
Check the thermos on this nightstand for me.
你帮我看看这床头柜上边这个暖水瓶
There are two characters on it.
上边有俩字
What's this second character?
这后边这字是什么？
The paint's worn off the bottle.
这水瓶掉漆了
Duh—why else would I ask you?
废话，那干嘛让你看？
"Hui."
“会”
The character "hui."
“会”字
Let's see.
看看
Captain Ma, Chief Zhu called a meeting.
马队，朱局喊开会了
Calling a meeting now of all times.
在这时候喊开会
Here.
给
Save it for when I'm back.
留着一会回来吃吧
Let me get a sip—so thirsty.
我来口水，太渴了
There's no water here.
这没水呀还
Hurry...
赶紧…
Chief Zhu.
朱局
Sit.
坐下
Chief Zhu.
朱局
This so-called Hong Kong businessman is really from Zhanjiang, Guangdong.
这个所谓的港商其实是广东湛江人
He registered a company in Hong Kong.
在香港注册了公司
On the 5th, he spoke with his driver by phone.
5号他跟司机通了个电话
Then he became unreachable.
然后就联系不上了
Before vanishing, he received an 800,000-yuan money order from Hualin Steel.
他失踪之前 收了一张桦钢八十万的汇票
The bank says someone tried to cash it.
银行那边反映有人去提过这个钱
So we suspect this may not be a simple economic case.
所以我们怀疑这案子 可能不是简单的经济案件
Are you on top of this, Ma Desheng?
这情况你掌握不，马德胜？
What kind of captain are you?
你这队长是怎么当的？
None of us have been idle.
都没闲着
I want results.
我要的是结果
Drop the dismemberment case.
碎尸案的事你别管了
Hand it to the main squad.
交给总队吧
You all now go all-out
你们现在就全力以赴
on the cash-withdrawal lead.
抓住提现的这个线索
First find out who tried to cash that money.
先给我摸清楚是谁要提这个钱
Find...
摸…
Definitely on it.
肯定摸
I never said I wouldn't investigate.
没说不查呀
Give me two days—till I'm back from Songhe.
等我两天，等我从松河回来
Why Songhe?
去松河干啥？
I suspect the guy who took Shen Mo's nudes and wrote the anonymous letter
我怀疑给沈墨拍裸照 写匿名信的这家伙
had an unusual relationship with her.
跟沈墨的关系不一般
I'm heading to Songhe right away—alone.
我马上去趟松河，我自己去
I'll question her family thoroughly.
我再仔细问问他家属
Ma Desheng, do you not understand what I'm saying?
马德胜，我说话你是不是听不懂呀？
I can't work on anything else right now.
我现在干不了别的
Those body parts are just lying there.
那尸块就在那放着呢
We're this close to a lead.
眼看就有线索了
What if the guy really runs?
这人要真跑了怎么办？
Ma Desheng, you are a police officer.
马德胜，你是一个警察
You must do your duty on every case.
对每一个案子都要尽职尽责
I am a cop—
我是警察
and this is a homicide.
这人命案
Chief Zhu.
朱局
I have some thoughts on the missing businessman.
这个港商失踪的事我有点想法
How about I watch the withdrawal lead for Captain Ma for two days?
要不那个追查提现的事 我先替马队盯两天？
Stay out of it. This doesn't concern you.
你别吱声，这跟你没关系
How does it not?
怎么没关系呀？
He's a cop too.
他也是警察
(The People's Police Serve the People)
（人民公安为人民）
The bag.
包
Driving there alone this late?
这大晚上的，一个人开车去呀？
What? You want to come along?
怎么的？ 你要跟我一块去呀？
Get in. I'll drive you.
上车吧，我给你开
Better help Li Qun with the money order.
你还是帮李群弄那汇票的事吧
I'll be fine—back first thing tomorrow.
我啥事没有，明天一早就回来了
Don't keep bringing him up to me.
以后你别老跟我提他
You saw that just now, right?
刚才你都瞅见了吧？
Him, offering opinions.
他还提上意见了
Is it his place?
轮得着他吗？
The nerve of him.
不够他嚣张的
He did take some heat off me.
他也算帮我挡了火力了
All right, I'm off.
行了，走了啊
Got a smoke?
有烟吗？
What? Not quitting anymore?
怎么的？ 不戒了？
Forget it.
算了